Countdown to the NFL Draft is officially
on where the Cardinals have the third
overall pick. From the Cardinals
interview suite at the NFL Scouting
Combine in Indianapolis, I'm Dani Soreck
joined by general manager Monti
Ossenfort. Monti, after you assess the
2025 season, what foundational pieces
are you building upon for 2026? Yeah,
Dani. I mean, listen, it was the season
didn't go as well as we wanted to. And
so, we have we got a lot of room to grow
and a lot of room to add pieces to our
team. And so, that process starts now.
It's been going on since the season
ended.
Um you know, two major ten poles of
roster building occur here back-to-back
in free agency and the draft. And this
is the next step in the player
evaluation process. And so, we had a lot
a lot of good young pieces. A lot of
young players got a chance to play this
year in the in 2025. That's only going
to serve them well moving forward. And
you know, we're going to continue to add
to the team um through this process. And
the combine's a good step in the right
direction. Every team wants to improve
everywhere in the off season. Which
specific parts of the game overall are
most pressing for you to address in the
off season?
>> Yeah, I mean, I think listen, I think
everywhere. Every year is a new team. Um
you know, there's the constant change in
the NFL on rosters.
Um and that's no different to us. Every
every team goes through it. And so, you
know, what may not look like a need at
one point can quickly become a need. And
so, you know, there's we're trying to
improve every aspect of our team and
increase the competition at every
position. And you know, there's there's
no place that we're going to say, "Well,
we're we're all set at this position."
So, uh always looking to make our team
better and we can do that in a in a many
number of ways. You have the third
overall pick, seven picks total. It's a
non-quarterback heavy draft. What
opportunities does that provide you with
sitting at the top? Yeah, I mean, I
think every draft is different. You
know, every draft has uh strong
positions, weak positions. That's the
truth for for every draft that comes
every year. And so, our job is to
evaluate the players that are available
and to to be ready to go. And so, you
know, picking number three, it's a
blessing and a curse. You know, we don't
want to be picking up this high um you
know, in the future. But you know, we
know that we're going to get a good
player there. And we're going to have
opportunities to improve our team. And
so, whatever that position whatever
position that ball's on uh it's going to
be a player that can that can help our
team. And so, it's our job to from here
on out figure out who has the most value
for us at that position and we'll be
ready to take that player. Four
first-round picks in your tenure. What's
the number one quality you look for to
make someone worthy of that honor? Yeah,
I mean, a lot goes into that. Like our
our scouts put a lot of time and effort
into evaluating the players, um evalu-
evaluating them on the field, off the
field. And then that continues here as
we involve our our coaches in the
process. Um and so, we put a lot of time
and effort into figuring out just
exactly how that player is going to fit
for our team. So, you know, that's a
that's a big decision that comes with
making a making any selection, not just
in the first round. And we we have to
check a lot of boxes before we feel
comfortable taking a player. And so,
whether that's in the first round or the
seventh round, like it's a it a player
has to go through a lot of processes to
for us to be comfortable with them. And
so, we're going to do the same thing. We
have a new new staff this year, new
staff coming in. They're busy hard at
work. This is the first chance for the
coaches to to sit down with those
players.
Um and you know, we'll continue through
our process and and we'll be ready to to
make the best selection for our team. 28
picks with the Cardinals for you. Where
have you grown the most as an evaluator
and a general manager in those three
years?
>> Yeah, I mean, I think as an evaluator
you grow every year. I mean, you can
never um you can never see enough
players and you know, comparison. You
know, this this player reminds me of a
another player I may have seen in the
past. You know, and I think I think just
going through the process and and seeing
where we want to tweak things, to see
where we want to adjust and see what we
want to do differently.
Um you know, we have we have an idea of
how our process is run, but we're always
trying to get better. And so, we'll do
that every year. And I think just this
the experience, the time on task and and
there's no um there's no playbook for
exactly how to how to run a draft and
how to be a general manager. It changes
every day. There's new things that come
across my plate. And so, just the
experience of going through it, you
know, I think there's no there's no
replication for for experience and and
uh feel that each year try to get better
at at everything that we do. One of the
new experiences this year is having
Michael Flores the head coach and his
staff that he has put together. How do
you tow the line of building a team your
way as the GM while incorporating what
your head coach wants? Yeah, I mean, I
think that's that's always a part of
roster building. And so, you know, it's
our it's our job as as scouting
department, as a personnel department to
understand how it is that
uh that coach Ossenfort and his staff
wants to play the game from a schematic
standpoint. Um you know, I think we see
things very similar in terms of the type
of people that we're looking for, the
people that are uh you know, mature,
dependable, going to put football first,
uh going to put the team first. So, that
that's an easy part of it. And so,
that's we got to continue to strive to
to figure out who the people are.
Uh and then just understanding what
exactly sche- schematically that the
players are going to be asked to do so
that we can go out as a scouting
department and find those players that
can fit that vision. One of those
collaborations that you have to work on
together is at the quarterback position.
You've said everything is on the table
regarding Kyler Murray's future. What
makes the magnitude of that decision,
given the position, different than the
other decisions you're going to have to
make? Yeah, I think with every decision
as it goes into our roster, we we put a
lot of time and effort into finding the
right people for the team and and the
people that can perform at a high level.
And so, whether it's the quarterback
position or the offensive line,
defensive line,
uh we we put a lot of time and effort
into all that and figuring that out. So,
uh you know, those decisions aren't
taken lightly and and we have to it's
our job as as just to serve the
organization to put the best group of
players out on the field. You said you
wanted to see more player development
starting this year. Where does that
affect your draft decisions in terms of
a player that can come in and start day
one versus a player that might need more
development?
>> Yeah, I mean, I think that I think that
is challenging. It's always challenging.
This is that's a big jump from a player
to make for going from college football
to the NFL. It's a it's a completely
different game and you're talking about
maturity and development physically,
mentally. So, that that's a challenge.
So, guys that can make that transition
that quickly, uh that's an impressive
feat to do. And so, that's always a
balance. There's always guys that are
further along in their development,
maybe a little bit more ready to
contribute. Um but you know, that's
always that's going to be the case for
every draft. But ultimately, it's about
finding the right type of person that
can do the things that we want to do
schematically. And whether that's game
one or further down the line or maybe
even down the line in year two. But it's
really about finding the right people
that fit our program. Just between you
and I, Monti. Who are you taking at
three?
Dani, let's talk in a few months and
then we'll get that squared away. How's
that sound? Oh, that's fine. Can't say I
didn't try. Cardinals fans, I I did my
best. We appreciate the time, Monti.
Cardinals are going to be on the clock
soon enough at the end of April, third
overall pick in the NFL Draft. We've got
more coverage from the NFL Scouting
Combine. For Monti Ossenfort, I'm Dani
Soreck. Thanks so much for tuning in.